so in this uh in one suit that would
have said
that one cannot develop
one cannot develop
the right view if
one hasn't
grasped the sign of his own mind
and one cannot grasp the sign of his own
one cannot grasp the sign of his own
mind if one has not become accomplished
in solitude hasn't been dwelling in
physical seclusion
so what is then the sign of the mind
well like um
in brief terms it's really just
learning how to discern your own mind as
how to discern your own mind as
as an enduring thing right here right
now usually people can um can
usually people can um can
discern and have such attitude
and see things as things
on the level of their own senses only on
the level of the sense of objects so
even then
so that's kind of the um
the the the standard
of of the way things would be attended
to
the measure the measure of thinness of
of what it is it's pretty much
what you can access and see
and perceive through your five senses
so
but the mind is not
it's not on that level when people turn
then that type of attention that's been
cultivated on the level of sense objects
when they turn their type of attention
to their own mind it's not the mind that
they see
it's pretty much another assumed
thing on the level and that assumption
is still on the level of the sense
objects so then that which is the mind
so then that which is the mind
there at a time it's not seen because
the mind does not appear on the level of
the five senses
and the mind is certainly not an object
of the senses in the same you know an
ear cannot hear itself and eyes cannot
see itself
so the problem is then when people turn
to
try to discern and investigate the mind
their tools are tools of their senses
which they use to you know
find the mind
the the
the tools of the sense objects and
they're simply not compatible for for
the domain where the mind exists
so that's the the whole
nimita the limit of the signs and
features see that's something that is um that
see that's something that is um that
cannot be
accessed directly
through the attention
that you use to cultivate it towards
sense objects like
me the subject here is the object i'm
attend to it i'm examining it i'm
looking at the details of it i'm
figuring it out that only works on the
level of relationship between sense and
object so and that's pretty much yes all the
so and that's pretty much yes all the
all the modern science
the the various branches of it it's
always the same principle observer and
the observed
so
that principle does not work if you want
to understand your mind because the mind
cannot be observed as an object
so that's why people you know people do
realize this people who have tried and
they get a get an inkling that it
doesn't quite work the approach the
tools you use
to to investigate and figure out the
mind it they're not quite compatible but
then that's when people kind of fall
into the other sort of um
extreme let's say like that which is
when they start to mystify to them they
start to mystify the mind as that which
is always there and it's always present
and the knower the watcher the observer
whatever else is
implying that uh it can be left alone on
that ambiguous level
and uh and sort of given some sort of
higher role of some some you know
mystical entity
that um
that it's uh well again that again
results in the same
uh level of uh not knowing what that
mind actually is
so grasping the signs of the mind that
the buddha talks about is something that
can that's then in between
so it's in between observance of the
sense object and it's in between of uh
mystifying that background that what's
behind that observer
it's it's understanding what is there
enduring as phenomena as we often say
so how to see the mind as phenomena well
that's that nimita part whereby you
start to discern signs and features of
it
uh because
signs and features are always secondary
are always peripheral to to the thing
that you're directly observing
so even on the level of that
relationship between observer and the
observed senses in the sense objects
when you're looking at something
what that thing means what they think
implies uh what the thing signifies
uh what the thing signifies
is not what you're seeing
so when you look at the sign that says
stop the simplest example often used in
the simplest example often used in
philosophy
you are seeing the shape the color the
sign the letters but see the meaning now
of that word that you are perceiving
is not what you're seeing with your eyes
is what you know with your mind
simultaneously there
and what is that meaning well that
meaning is do not cross this
do not go past this point
or whatever else it means
that meaning is found peripheral to what
you're looking at
and the only reason the meaning is there
is because that's where the mind is
there so learning to see these signs and
so learning to see these signs and
features without having to attend to
them directly on the level of that
observer observed sense objects senses
sense objects is how you
you're learning to discern limiter
the phenomenon of nimitz recognizing
that there are such things that exist
peripherally only when i don't look at them directly
only when i don't look at them directly
only when i don't attend to them they
exist for what they are as such
if you were to say attend now to one of
those nimitas to one of those
significances meanings implications that
you know
that will become then the object of your
attention the object of your
senses so in other words something else now
so in other words something else now
would be animator to that
something else would now be the
peripheral significance of what you are
looking at directly as an object of your
attention so the mind in that sense the mind is
so the mind in that sense the mind is
always peripheral the mind is always on
the level of where those nimitz
significances and features are
so
learning how to see
signs and features of any phenomena does
not mean examining signs and features in
the detail and learning the information
about them means seeing them as
phenomena seeing them on the level that
they are
without giving into that pressure to
attend to them and examine them on the
level of sense observation that you
would do with your eyes or in like a
scientific experiment
and that's how you cultivate your mind
then that's that's the whole like the
context we often talk to context is
something that's always peripheral
so the whole the whole practice of
discerning limiters
is pretty much the correct practice of
mindfulness where your mindfulness is
not on the level of attending to the
moment-to-moment experience but it's on
the level of knowing the significance of
currently enduring experience as such
um and then refraining from attending to
it as in refraining from overly trying
to access it and refraining from
mystifying it
like you realize you can't access it directly
you realize you can't access it directly
so then you mystify it you make it
more than it actually is
but in reality it exists as such as a
peripheral phenomena there with
everything else
so
significances of your
sights and smell test touches are all
limiters of sights and small test
touches and now if you learn how to see
limiters on the level of sight sound
smell taste touches this enduring body
here the significance is if you train
your mind in that peripheral recognition
exactly you're training your mind by
default in regard to anything so sooner or later
in regard to anything so sooner or later
these nimitas there's nothing mystical
about them by the way we covered it in
previous talks
so these significances
will now start to be seen even in regard
to the mind
so the features the characteristics the
implications that of the mind that
endures there as a thing as a phenomenon
this this sense of an individual
you can say observer there's there's no
need to deny that the unity that
observes so to speak
and you just need to see the signs and
features of that you just need to see
what is peripheral to that which is
generally quite ambiguous and peripheral
for somebody who is too dependent on the
sense objects so so that's why the the
the whole um
prerequisite for discerning this level
of um
subtlety of signs and features in regard
to the mind
uh the prerequisite is pretty much the
uh like sensory strain guarding of the
sensors and then dwelling in physical
seclusion like being completely alone
then that which the mind is
that which the mind is
emerged as a thing there peripheral
thing again you don't need to stop
looking or learn how to see it with your
eyes and so on because it's impossible
it completely exists in its own domain
that it's inaccessible to your five
senses but it's there as such as a
domain inaccessible to the five senses
that you can know
so the the practice then of mindfulness
is the practice of seeing the state of
the mind enduring there
for what it is
as such on its own
with this external world of the senses
and sense objects
so
whether you are thinking about the mind
and the thoughts specific thoughts
whether you are absorbed into the sense
objects through your senses the mind is
there enduring as such on a peripheral
level and if you if you have trained in
the discernment of the peripheral you
will be seeing it doesn't matter how far
that phenomenon is
within you
it is still here and now
whatever else is going on in front of
you that mind endures as such
so uh
discerning the cheetah emitter means
discerning the signs and features of the
mind means seeing the mind
as a phenomena independent of you that
induce on its own level
see people can sort of
try to apply the view that oh yes this
mind doesn't belong to me nothing is
myself it's just there like a thing but
that view
uh is
practically and usually and most
commonly applied through the assumptions
of sense
and sense objects that's the measure of
existence so when somebody too dependent
on the sense objects
thinks about this level of subtle
existence they won't see it so when they
refer to the mind from the point of view
of their assumptions in the view they
just refer to it as another external
object that's on the level of the
observation by their senses
and that's why even in the whole you
know science the western science in
particular um the whole relationship
with like the mind consciousness
thoughts always will boil down to some
you know physical
and chemical presence and balances and
hormones and things that you can measure
and observe assuming that that's where
the mind is because there is nothing
else that you can see with your eyes
there is nothing else you can be
narrowing it down to the smallest
particles in particulars
and since there's nothing else that you
can see the natural assumption will
assume oh that's the center in the brain
for the consciousness or the mind or
whatever else is failing to understand
that the principle of observation
already requires your mind being there
that cannot be seen on that level and
that's something that a scientist
western scientists will be thoroughly
ignorant of and unaware of
so the practice of mindfulness is not
about merging the approach of the
science and the buddhist teaching the
practice of mindfulness is completely
overcoming the pressure of attending to
things as a measure of existence and
seeing what is peripheral to it what are
the signs and features of the pressure
of the measure of existence of my sense
objects because even the sense
dependence and sensuality and attending
to the objects of um
of your senses requires the mind being
there and signs and features of that are
always accessible and visible
so physical seclusion then is is pretty
much the practice whereby you are not
engaging too too much
or too distractingly with the external
world upon which by the way your views still
upon which by the way your views still
depend because nobody starts enlightened
you already start dependent on the sense
objects depending on the world depending
on over attending is the measure of the
normal attending and you don't see
anything peripheral so withdrawal and
physical seclusion and dwelling in
non-company and all of that upon you
know the proper virtue and
sense restraint and guiding of the sense
those that then becomes your practice of uh
that then becomes your practice of uh
through that non
uh or through not overly engaging with
external world you still operate in that
solitude and then you get to see
then you know like the movements the
thoughts you have the perceptions you
have you start to discern that unity of
the mind uh as like a container as a
framework of all these particular
engagements that you have on a of a
neutral kind with a sense objects
through your senses
so that's what dwelling in solitude is
necessary because it takes time to
discern that framework
of of uh seeing smelling tasting
touching standing walking and so on and
that framework is not to be mystified
but to be understood on the level that
it is which is the level of the
peripheral it's always
peripheral um it's always the background
of that which you're looking at that
which you're smelling that which you are
tasting that which you're touching and
you are always doing some of these
things senses are there operating in the
world so pretty much discerning the
science of the mind means discerning the
domain that is wider and more primordial
not first but more fundamental in a
sense it's the container to the domain of the
it's the container to the domain of the
senses and that's where the mind comes
first as the as the the suttas and our
partner would say
the framework the mood the direction of
your mind the intent all these things
are on the level of the mind and all
those things pretty much determine your
behavior determine your engagement with
the senses and everything else
so that's why that is the prerequisite
for understanding the the escape from
suffering the four noble truths for
becoming a sodopana
when you're trying to understand the
mind and you're trying to get into the
details of it that which your mind is is
peripheral to that experience of your
effort to understand the mind so in
other words
wherever whatever you've been attending
with your perception and
with your mind you discern signs and
features of that that you're not
attending at the same time
and on that level is where your mind is
on that level is where your mind is
so so training to see that without
needing to look at it that's the whole
practice and um and the more you develop that the
and um and the more you develop that the
the steadier that image becomes the the
less perturbable that image becomes
which means the more composure your mind
has the better samadhi has been
developed and
and
when that samadhi is sufficient when
that imperturbability is sufficient when
that knowledge of the signs and features
of the mind knowledge of the mind as a
phenomena seeing the mind for what it is
on the level that it is without needing
to attend it overly attending
underattended and all of these
sort of
mistaken efforts around it seeing it for
what it is is the prerequisite for
seeing this gift from suffering why
because if you see the mind for what it
is as a thing enduring there truly on
its own as a phenomenon without your
interference that's already a form of seeing an utter
that's already a form of seeing an utter
seeing understanding impermanence
understanding the non-ownership of it and above all uh
the non-ownership of it and above all uh
seeing the gratuity of the craving
that implies the ownership the implies
that directionality that comes from your
mind so so seeing the mind as a phenomena is
so so seeing the mind as a phenomena is
a prerequisite for for uprooting the
craving and
and
that's why fully developing the
knowledge of the uh the chittanimita
results in the right view which means
results in fully understanding what
cessation of craving would be
and what complete freedom from suffering
what complete freedom from suffering
would entail and imply
so
physical solitude for which
is a prerequisite for that sound
developing the signs of the mind seeing
them correctly for which as i said many
times before
uh sense restraint moderation eating
guarding of the sense doors watchfulness
um
keeping obviously the precepts and the
virtues is an absolute must because you
will not be dwelling in solitude rightly
if you haven't been practicing these
things correctly beforehand
so it's not just a question of oh i'll
just go and lock myself alone
because you would still be attending to
things wrongly and you will not have
enough mental strength
to resist
um the pull of the attention that's
dependent on the sense objects because
of the you know all the current
ignorance and prior lack of sense
restraints and chasing with the pleasure
of the sense objects and so on
so that's why
in order to be able to dwell in solitude
correctly you need to have been you know properly
you need to have been you know properly
established in virtue guarding of the
sense doors and taken that as a training
not as some sort of
uh
behavior and level of observance that i
would do so that the enlightenment would
happen to me but as a direct training of
no this is the point the point is to
train every day of my life
every day of my life
in not giving into certain things in not
in not making certain choices and acting
out of them and so on
so that's already the form of
development and the form of
strengthening that container which then
when you take into solitude
uh you will get to
properly benefit from so then the mind
would emerge the shapes of it the the
contours the peripheral sort of signs
and features
of that basis of the framework that
induced that that living individual that
observer that everything else
is now seen there at the same time as
not something that belongs to you
because it takes it takes a sufficient
amount of that development of that
peripheral mindfulness
mindfulness
where you learn how to see things
without needing to look directly at them
needing to look directly at them
to get to see the mind on that
peripheral level
enduring saying like the things in the
world that you look at smell taste and
touch and
and
when that's fully developed that's
pretty much there is absolutely no room
then left for any passion aversion and
distraction to arise
in other words there will be no room
left for any craving to be manifested
and and that's in itself it's just end of
and that's in itself it's just end of
sensuality and suffering and any
any adversity pretty much that's it